<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Blog</title>
    <description>Abhijit Tomar&#39;s blog</description>
    <link>blog.abhijittomar.com/</link>
    <atom:link href="blog.abhijittomar.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Thu, 06 Jul 2017 23:51:56 +0530</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 06 Jul 2017 23:51:56 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.1.6</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Dubai Review</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Three hours post arriving in Dubai, I was depressed. Why the hell is the traffic so orderly? Why is everything so clean? It felt eerily robotic. If I was supposed to behave this way, I wasn’t ready for it. As an Indian, it was almost as if my free will had been stolen from me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I walked into my hotel lobby and heard a bunch of Chinese tourists yammering. The receptionist shouted to the security person “Abbe inn logon ko chup karwa” (Ask these guys to shut up). This is when I realised two things - one, a large part of the Dubai workforce is Indian. Two, there are a lot of Chinese tourists. How do I know they were Chinese and not Japanese or Taiwanese or Korean? Moving on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, quick intro- Dubai is one of the seven states of the UAE (United Arab Emirates). Abu Dhabi is the biggest and richest state of UAE and also the capital. Dubai? The second largest, second richest. Rest five? You’re not going to remember it anyway so let’s not delve into it. When the UAE was being formed in 1971, two states opted not to join - they were Bahrain and Qatar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;December 7 2016: Day 1 on my itinerary was to have dinner on a traditional boat called a Dhow. Dubai is divided into two parts - Bur and Deira by the Dubai creek which is where the Dhow cruise operates. Though nothing exceptional, it is worth a casual visit. Watch out for the pesky photographers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dubai is the city of the rich. But before 1966 it wasn’t. The founding fathers - who were fishermen and pearl divers - decided to settle close to sea to keep watch for incoming intruder ships.
On day 2, I visited the Dubai Museum and noticed it’s small size. Small is not usually a word you’d associate with Dubai. Compared to India, the cultural history is essentially inexistent. It was just a bunch of fishing villages, with a bunch of good people, which a bunch of bad guys used to keep attacking - regular stuff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before I continue I would like to lay to rest one myth about Dubai which several people (including my tour guide) are guilty of perpetuating. The price of water is NOT higher than that of oil. I was able to purchase a 1.5L bottle of packaged drinking water for 1.5 AED (about 30 INR) - this is similar to the rates in any other country. I went to a petrol pump and petrol was selling for 1.68 AED a litre while diesel was 1.81 AED a litre. So there you are folks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/dubai-review/burjalarab.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;burjalarab&quot; style=&quot;width:250px;&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Just a regular tall building&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dubai is home to some iconic buildings which I witnessed on my city tour (also day 2). The Jumeirah beach is right next to the Burj Al Arab - an exceptionally fancy hotel. Legend has it that Sheikh Mohammed was unimpressed with the existing 5 star hotel on the beach front. So he called his construction company, “Can I have a better hotel on the beach? Make it tall. Yeah, tallest in the world tall is fine. Now what do I colour the walls? Forget it, just cover it with gold. Oh, and put that on an artificial island 300m from the shore.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Dubai you have malls every 500m. It has been ensured that in case you get a sudden urge to splurge, you won’t be left hanging. So where’s Burj Khalifa? It’s right next to the world’s biggest mall of course. The Dubai Mall has an area of more than 1 million sq.m (that’s 1km square) and the store of probably every brand in existence. There are 5 Starbucks outlets and you need a map to navigate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/dubai-review/cayan.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;cayan-tower&quot; style=&quot;width:250px;&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Another tall building, but with a twist&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My last stop for Day 2 was At The Top, Burj Khalifa - which disappointingly, is not at the top. It is at the 124th floor. The elevator is FAST and your ears will pop from the sudden pressure change. The view from the top is beautiful. Despite the height, it doesn’t “feel” tall. It is like being in an aeroplane. Though an airplane is not something you want to see close by when you’re there. I asked my sister to keep watch for any incoming planes while I went to find an engineer to enquire about the melting point of the steel beams used in the construction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Khalifa, for all it’s sophistication, couldn’t rid itself of those annoying Chinese salesmen and women who keep shouting “SAAAAR PHOTO!!!” Seriously guys? I just paid $50 for entry to this thing and now..? Nevermind, I’ll just write an angry review somewhere and pretend my opinion matters.
If you plan to visit, book in advance for an evening slot (post 6pm). Then wait for the Dubai Fountain show which takes place every half an hour and looks even better from the top.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/dubai-review/burjkhalifa.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;burj-khalifa&quot; style=&quot;width:250px;&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Ye Burj Khalifa hai Mia&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The entirety of Day 3 was spent exploring the waterpark at Atlantis Hotel on Palm Island. 10/10 would do again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Coming back to the oil. That’s where UAE gets the money from. The rates are almost half we have in India. This is why cars are something Dubai loves. I prepared a list of the most common cars I saw on the roads -&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Toyota Corolla: Most common taxi. You will realise why it is the largest selling car in the world when you see their number on Dubai’s roads.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Toyota Land Cruiser: This is logical because even with a small nuclear family of two wives and two kids from each, a guy would need a car with 7 seats to accommodate them. This is where the third row seating of the Land Cruiser comes in handy.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Land Rover: When you’re rich with a small nuclear family but don’t want to go the mainstream Land Cruiser way. This is also the car used in the Desert Safari. (Day 4 for me).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;American muscle cars (Dodge Challenger/Charger, Ford Mustang, Chevrolet Camaro): Quite common. When you’re kinda rich but not rich enough to afford a real sports car.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Hatchbacks: Small is not a word associated with Dubai. This is also the reason why there are almost no hatchbacks.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
A large part of the credit for the success of UAE goes to the rulers. The President (who is always from Abu Dhabi) is Sheikh Khalifa bin Zayed Al Nahyan, while the Prime Minister (who is always from Dubai) is Sheikh Mohammed bin Rashid Al Maktoum. Their family basically owns the whole country, and they command everything while sitting in palaces of gold. Yet unlike a lot of rich kids, they had the sense to use the money to develop the country as a tourist destination to ensure their relevance when the oil runs out. YOLO - hence responsible future planning.
While the Sheikh and his family are indeed rich beyond imagination, they have done quite a bit to share some of the prosperity with their brethren. And as is required for tourism, they also graciously allowed in immigrants to work, setup their own companies, practise their own religion. There are caveats though. You can only own land if you’re a citizen, oh, and it’s impossible to get citizenship. And if you’re looking to setup a business in Dubai, an LLC, you need a local sponsor. Despite the name, he will not invest anything in your company but you need to pay him several thousand dollars a year for no reason.
Undeterred by the strict laws, Indians love it. There are several Hindi TV and radio channels. Bollywood actors are often seen in advertisements on hoardings and Indian companies are everywhere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally to recap the itinerary (Dec 7-11 2016) along with my ratings for each -&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Day 1: Arrival in afternoon, Dhow cruise dinner (3.5/5)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Day 2: City tour (including Dubai museum, Jumeirah Beach)(2.5/5), Dubai Mall and Burj Khalifa(4/5)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Day 3: Lost Chambers aquarium and Aquaventure waterpark @ Atlantis The Palm (4.5/5)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Day 4: Desert Safari in Sharjah followed by entertainment and dinner in desert camp (3/5)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Day 5: Return&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Cost: 60k and above (depending on itenerary)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
So would I recommend visiting this place to anyone? Definitely. Yes, it’s artificial. But it’s fabulous. See what man can make out of nothing (with a bit of money for motivation). Come and witness it while it lasts.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 04 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>blog.abhijittomar.com/2017/07/04/dubai-review/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">blog.abhijittomar.com/2017/07/04/dubai-review/</guid>
        
        
        <category>Travel</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>A student&#39;s guide to freelancing</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This article is a follow-up to the freelancing session conducted by Abhijit Tomar and Harshit Manocha at IIT Bombay on 17th of September 2016. It is intended to be a primer for any student looking to work as a part time freelancer. Two paths will be covered- those of a developer and a designer.
This post will cover the broad topics of:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#why-freelancing&quot;&gt;Why freelancing?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#a-students-approach&quot;&gt;A student’s approach&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#opportunities-overview&quot;&gt;Opportunities overview&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#online-freelancing&quot;&gt;Online freelancing&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#avoiding-common-issues&quot;&gt;Avoiding common issues&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#staying-grounded&quot;&gt;Staying grounded&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#getting-the-right-client&quot;&gt;Getting the right client&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#before-a-deal&quot;&gt;Before a deal&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#into-a-deal&quot;&gt;Into the deal&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#tips&quot;&gt;Tips&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
 &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;a-namewhy-freelancingawhy-freelancing&quot;&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;why-freelancing&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Why freelancing?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You may want to get into freelancing for three reasons:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;To learn&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a student, freelancing can be a great way to learn. It can provide an insight into how companies work. Working on live projects with actual goals and deadlines gives you a real-world experience that is not easily achieved in the safe, classroom setting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;To earn&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even if you are not short on cash, freelancing can be a way to earn some pocket money. The feeling of independence it provides is worth putting in the hours for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Skill building&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While working, you are simultaneously building your technical skills. This can open doors to bigger and better opportunities in future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;a-namea-students-approachaa-students-approach&quot;&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;a-students-approach&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;A student’s approach&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a student, the right approach is to optimise learning, rather than monetary returns.
For instance, if you are an experienced frontend web developer, the logical move is to venture into backend developement - even if your immediate earning potential is higher in frontend. A similar ideology can be applied in the design side. If you are experienced in UI/UX design, try exploring things like branding or social media.
By working on varying projects, you will gain a diverse, heterogeneous skillset that is more valuable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;a-nameopportunities-overviewaopportunities-overview&quot;&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;opportunities-overview&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Opportunities Overview&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The following are the kind of opportunites currently seen in the market:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Web (frontend)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every start-up or small business needs a website. And making those websites needs web developers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Android &amp;amp; iOS&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve never seen a jobless Android developer. The current market demand for Android developers is &lt;strong&gt;too damn high&lt;/strong&gt;. As long as Apple is in business, every company will also need an iOS app. Since iOS development requires an iDevice, the supply of iOS developers in the market is less, and are hence valued higher.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Backend (web and app)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To get work as a backend developer, you need frontend and Android dev friends who will recommend you :)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Blogging / Content Writing&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I could give you 17 reasons why anyone can be a blogger these days. However, demand for serious bloggers and content writers also exists depending on your domain expertise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Creative Design&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am using this as an umbrella term for the various creative services required by business. It may include UI/UX design, poster and logo design, video editing, branding etc. In this field, it is difficult to build a reputation. But once you’ve earned a name for yourself, it can be very lucrative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;a-nameonline-freelancingaonline-freelancing&quot;&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;online-freelancing&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Online freelancing&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are several websites that serve as platforms for freelancers to meet clients. For a small percentage of your earnings, these websites will get you clients, and implement some form of an escrow system to ensure that both parties are treated fairly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://freelancer.com&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Freelancer&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This happens to be among the popular ones. Here, you need to compete against other freelancers to get your proposal selected. A series of rejections can get disheartening since your work on the bid goes to waste.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://upwork.com&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Upwork&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This may be a better option for someone looking to make a stable income. You make your profile and list your hourly rate. Start at low rates, rack up good reviews and earn your way to a larger hourly rate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://toptal.com&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Toptal&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have reason to believe that your skills are better than the majority of professionals in your field, then this is the place for you. Toptal advertises itself to host the crème de la crème in the freelancing world. You can naturally expect to be paid higher than on other platforms (given you are able to clear the selection process). However, it is only for full-time freelancers. So, if you want to make a career in freelancing this is what you should be aiming for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;a-nameavoiding-common-issuesaavoiding-common-issues&quot;&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;avoiding-common-issues&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Avoiding common issues&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There can be many issues (pesky clients) you may run into while working as a freelancer. Some of them are:
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/student-freelancing/dilbert-comic.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;dilbert-comic&quot; style=&quot;width:250px; float:left; margin:20px&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Technically challenged clients&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have worked with clients, who even after several months had no idea what I &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; did (I work as a backend developer). You will often meet who will have difficulty wrapping their head around what you work on. Since they have zero knowledge of technical matters, it can be difficult for them to understand what is easy, difficult, or impossible to accomplish. It can also get difficult for you to justify how much you should be paid. Some view everything technical as the same black box and may have unreasonable demands (“Okay it’s almost done, but we just add a chat feature to this website? I’m sure it’s easy - every website has it these days.”). You will run into problems with this client due to not being able to communicate effectively (which may not be the fault of anyone in particular).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The future billionaire&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He is convinced his app / website is going to hit it big. His favourite sentence is “We are going to be the Uber of X”. Delusional is the word to describe this person. He will not feel stupid dropping the line, “This is a billion dollar idea…” on the first meeting. Unless he has a past record of creating multi-million dollar business, this is the point where you fake an emergency and promise to get back next week (never).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sleazy start-up guy&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hey! I can’t pay you right now, but you can be the CTO with X% equity in my startup. This may or may not be the future billionaire’s partner in crime. The first question you should ask yourself is, “Why did he so easily offer me 15% of his self-proclaimed billion dollar startup on the first meeting?” This can be for two reasons- either he knows the shares aren’t worth anything, or he believes they are and is gullible enough to give them to you on the first meeting. Dealing with such an insincere / slow person, you will only end up wasting your time. Avoid this person at all costs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;a-namestaying-groundedastaying-grounded&quot;&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;staying-grounded&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Staying grounded&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From the above representations you may think no one could fall for such obvious mistakes. However in real life the prospects offered can sound convincing and tempting. Most clients you deal with will have some degree of the above listed attributes. In such a scenario, it is important to keep a professional relation. Stay an arm’s length and do not get involved into the start-up more than your job requires. If you do get involved, do remember that most (even genuinely good) ideas fail for random reasons in the real world. You have better odds hitting it large in the powerball. Even if you have a great team with a clear gameplan, you will only likely be mildly successful at best.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;a-namegetting-the-right-clientagetting-the-right-client&quot;&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;getting-the-right-client&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Getting the right client&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a student, the act of freelancing is essentially brought down to choosing the right client. Try to get a client with the following qualities:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Has skills&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is no better to enhance your skills than to work with a more skilled team. Getting such a client can be made easier if you leave out the goal of making profits. If your only takeaway in the project is money, your takeaway in the long term is zero.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Someone you can trust&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I cannot stress how important this is. While working on real projects, there is a great deal that can go wrong. There are people out there who will screw you over at the first opportunity they get. Trust your instincts, if it doesn’t feel right it probably isn’t.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Someone you can learn from&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Learning can be not just technical. Most of the learning you will derive as a freelancer will be implicit and non-technical. You need someone with strong ethics and fundamentals in the field he/she is working.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Someone with brand value&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Working with a company / person who has already made it large in life can set you up for good things in future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;a-namebefore-a-dealabefore-a-deal&quot;&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;before-a-deal&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Before a deal&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Write. Everything. Down.&lt;/strong&gt; Making a website isn’t the same as knowing HTML/CSS. You need to write html/css/js code, get hosting, configure access controls, set up a webserver, set up software for production deployment, set up and configure the database, set up admin accounts and controls, get a domain name, configure dns, install an ssl certificate, install failsafe measures for the production server, ensure data backups at intervals, log activity, implement abuse prevention safeguards and test to ensure the website doesn’t contain vulnerabilities (non-exhaustive).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If it isn’t obvious yet, you need to be very clear about what you’re going to go and what you’re not. Do the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;—&amp;gt; Define scope of work clearly to prevent being exploited. Eg- “I’ll give three iterations. Every change from there is going to cost more”.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;—&amp;gt; Discuss the schedules and timeline. Run them through the client.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;—&amp;gt; Describe the deliverables for formatting / compatibility.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;—&amp;gt; If possible, show a demo deliverable from previous projects.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;—&amp;gt; Lay out the payment schedule. Prefer to be paid weekly, or partly in advance.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;a-nameinto-a-dealainto-a-deal&quot;&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;into-a-deal&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Into a deal&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;—&amp;gt; Don’t hand over the work until complete payment has been made. Your service is worth nothing to the client once he already has it.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;—&amp;gt; Be professional - use online tools for drafting proposals and invoices.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;—&amp;gt; Communicate with the client. Most problems can be solved with just a small chat.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;—&amp;gt; Notify progress and keep the client updated. Send out mail at least once a week.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;—&amp;gt; Be honest. Is it going to take you a day more? Most clients will be accomodating if you’re honest with them from the start.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;—&amp;gt; Undercommit and overdeliver. Don’t promise anything you can’t keep. The client would have been with two weeks, but you said one. Better to say two and surprise him.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;—&amp;gt; Even if the client asks for something extra later, just do it (given it doesn’t take too much time).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;—&amp;gt; Hand over work in proper format (git for developers, Dropbox / Google Drive for designers).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;—&amp;gt; Own the project. Work on it like it’s your baby. If you can do anything to make it better - even if it’s not your job - do it (again, time matters).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;a-nametipsatips&quot;&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;tips&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Tips&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;—&amp;gt; Look into forming a binding contract with the client (even if you trust him).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;—&amp;gt; Get a web presence (personal website / behance / dribble / facebook page).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;—&amp;gt; Just because they’re paying doesn’t mean you’re a slave. Lay out contact hours.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;—&amp;gt; Feel free to fire clients.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;—&amp;gt; If you don’t know how to do it, say yes and learn later :)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 20 Sep 2016 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>blog.abhijittomar.com/2016/09/20/student-freelancing/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">blog.abhijittomar.com/2016/09/20/student-freelancing/</guid>
        
        
        <category>Freelancing</category>
        
        <category>Web Development</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Intern Experience at Microsoft IDC, Bangalore</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;As a Mechanical engineer interested in software development, the internship season put me into a bit of a quandary. Since software companies seldom open for non-CS students, weeks had passed by without me signing a single IAF (Internship Application Form). In mid-August, Microsoft India Development Centre (MSIDC) came along. I had stood runner-up in code.fun.do (the Microsoft university hackathon) the previous year. Consequently, Microsoft invited me to participate in the internship selection process (which is otherwise open only to CS students) and I cashed in on the opportunity. This was my first insight into how well thought-out the Microsoft internship program is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;getting-there&quot;&gt;Getting There:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The selection process involved two rounds of coding. Shortlisted candidates were then invited for multiple rounds of interviews. Knowledge of algorithms and data structures is a prerequisite, where having done CS-213 (or equivalent like EE-717) would come in handy. Being familiar in backend development, the interviewer asked me several questions related to my field of expertise in addition to the standard data structures ones. I also found this knowledge to be highly useful during the course of my internship.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MSIDC hires for two locations in India – Hyderabad and Bangalore. I was assigned to the Dynamics CRM team at Bangalore. Dynamics CRM is an enterprise CRM (Customer Relationship Management) software. Not being a mass-market product, I had never even heard of this arm of Microsoft before. I was stumped to know that it makes over $1Billion in revenues and is still growing at a massive rate. It has now taken the second position in the segment, right behind Salesforce.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;about-the-company&quot;&gt;About the Company&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While I was sitting at my workstation with the source code, trying to figure out how this billion dollar application works, I knew that my work was the only thing I needed to worry about. Microsoft literally took care of everything else. It is rare, even among the best of employers to offer full provisions for accommodation, travel and food throughout the duration of the intern. The office was bang in the centre of the city. All interns were provided accommodation at a luxurious service apartment within a walking distance from the office. The food at the office was healthy and delicious. This is in addition to their well-stocked 24×7 pantry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What impressed me the most about Microsoft was their work culture. All the rules (or lack thereof) are an extension of pure logic. There are no in-out time requirements. You can work from home, or from the office for as long as you want. All you have to ensure is to get the work done in the allotted timespan – it’s that simple! People who are used to working independently would feel at-ease working here. There is no dress code over here – you can wear anything you feel like wearing (You will, however, feel awkward in formal clothing when your manager walks in wearing a tee and jeans). The organisation is extremely agile for a company this size. The focus is on getting the work done, than on frivolous rules or procedures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For my intern, my team gave me a completely new project to develop. I, and a fellow intern were the only people working on it. Due to the nature of the task, I am contractually bound to not disclose even a vague outline of the job description – at least until the feature is released to the public. The team was very open to inputs and we were given full freedom to suggest features, or methods to implement those features.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All my co-workers are extremely approachable. One of them was nice enough to even give me his own team jacket (thanks Tarun)! The managers, even at the highest levels have a good idea about the specifics of what everyone is working on. You will often have co-workers randomly challenging you to a game of carrom or foosball when you need a break. Not to be missed are the facilities for gymming, badminton, basketball, cricket, in addition to the tons of Xboxs lying around at every corner of the office.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/intern-msidc/tomar.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;le-me&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;bangalored&quot;&gt;Bangalored!&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had been allotted two very helpful mentors who guided me throughout the intern. One of them was possibly the coolest mentor an intern at Microsoft ever got (PM for more). I was also blessed to have been allotted the team which was most prolific in outings. I went out with my team for several lunches, dinners, a movie, and even an IPL match!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/intern-msidc/team.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;le-team&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The cherry on the cake was that since the intern is in Bangalore, where the largest chunk of students from IITB is interning, I went out with friends almost every weekend. There are several places to see around Bangalore – Coorg, Nandi Hills, Ooty; the list is endless. We managed to explore many of them. Bangalore is a trekker’s paradise. You can rent a bike/car and head out on the weekends on your own with traveller blogs and &lt;strike&gt;Google&lt;/strike&gt; Bing Maps coming to your rescue. There are also quite a few tour operators who will provide you with guides (recommended for medium to difficult treks). The weather in Bangalore is pleasant like that of Mumbai. It rained frequently throughout my intern right from May beginning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall, the internship has provided me a great insight into the software development industry. Knowing how the biggest and best companies pull off their work has been a valuable experience. Given the scale Microsoft provides, you know you’re working for something that is going to impact an enormous number of people (albeit, in an indirect, subconscious manner). Knowledge of this fact gives a very unique feeling of satisfaction that is difficult to describe. To sum it up – Microsoft consists of a bunch of really cool and smart people who live a way of life worth an experience.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 20 Jun 2016 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>blog.abhijittomar.com/2016/06/20/intern-msidc-bangalore/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">blog.abhijittomar.com/2016/06/20/intern-msidc-bangalore/</guid>
        
        
        <category>Internships</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
